<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and impartial narrative of the most material debates and passages in the late Parliament. Together with the rise and disolution of it, published for the satisfaction of those that desire to know how they spent their time. By a Member of that Parliament, who is none of the present Parliament.</title>
            <author>Bethel, Slingsby, 1617-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E985_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866896</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 146:E985[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and impartial narrative of the most material debates and passages in the late Parliament. Together with the rise and disolution of it, published for the satisfaction of those that desire to know how they spent their time. By a Member of that Parliament, who is none of the present Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Bethel, Slingsby, 1617-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 7-14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Brewster, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the three Bibles in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Member of that Parliament, who is none of the present Parliament = Slingsby Bethel.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 9.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true and impartial NARRATIVE OF The moſt material Debates and paſſages in the late <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi> TOGETHER With the Riſe and Diſolution of it, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for the ſatisfaction of thoſe that deſire to know how they ſpent their time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Member of that Parliament, who is none of the preſent Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſign of the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119184:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119184:2"/>
            <head>A true and perfect <hi>Narrative,</hi> of the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Debates and Paſſages in the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe over-ruling hand of Providence, having upon the third of <hi>September</hi> (a day of ſignal mercies unto this Nation) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the late Uſurper, whileſt he was in poſſeſſion of the Title of Protector of the Commonwealth, his Son <hi>Richard</hi> was the next day by the Councel at <hi>White Hall</hi> proclaimed his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor: He, by the Authority thereof, did, about three months after, iſſue out Writs for a Parliament to begin the 27th of <hi>January</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. The people who in their diffuſed condition, is capable on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of obeying their Superiors, and not of diſputing the legality, or illegality of their commands, made choice of Members to ſerve in Parliament, they according to their ſummons aſſembled upon the day appointed; when they were met, the pretended Protector ſent the black Rod to let them know that he was in the Other Houſe, and deſired to ſpeak to them there, at which call, not above ten or twelve went out of the Houſe, though more that was not come in appeared before him: Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> was that day choſen Speaker, and after a Bill unpaſſed left by the precedent Parliament, was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to cuſtom read, the Houſe Adjurned until the next day, Then a Gentleman was complained of for affronting two Members, and he ordered to be brought to the Bar of the Houſe by the Serjeant: A private Faſt in the Houſe, and the Miniſters to perform the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that day was appointed, a Committee for Elections and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges choſen, and ſo the Houſe Adjurned until the 31. of <hi>January,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119184:3"/>it being cuſtomary at the beginning of Parliaments, to give the Speaker a day or two to ſettle his own buſineſs, in that he may the better afterwards attend the ſervice of the Houſe. The Gentleman that affronted the Members was brought to the Bar upon his knees, and for his offence committed to the Tower; but in a few dayes, upon his ſubmiſſion, and at the interceſſion of the Gentlemen abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he was releaſed. The firſt of <hi>February</hi> a Bill was brought in by Mr. Secretary, under pretence only of acknowledging the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Protector, but under ſuch terms as had no leſs in them, than the admittance of the Chief Magiſtrate, and the Perſons then ſitting in the Other Houſe, unto the full power, privileges, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the ancient Kings, and ancient Houſe of Lords which the court party deſigned to have carried undiſcovered, and ſo have left the Nation, either to have fought the late quarrel over again, or elſe to be content with a bad change of perſons, where there was none of things.</p>
            <p>The Bill was that day without much difficulty read the firſt time, which encouraged thoſe of the long robe related to the ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to preſs for the reading of it again the ſame day to the end that it being the next day read the third time (as they deſigned it) it might have paſſed into an Act; but in oppoſition to that, ſome who were more careful of the Liberties of the people than thoſe of the long Robe ordinarily are, moved, that according to rule in caſes of ſuch weight, it might be referred to a grand Committee of the whole Houſe; and when that would not be granted, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reading of it might at leaſt be put off for ſome dayes, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty given to the Members to take Copies, that conſidering of the buſineſs, they might be the more fitting for the debate, which was yeilded unto, and the ſeventh of <hi>February</hi> appointed for the ſecond reading.</p>
            <p>The State of Major General <hi>Overtons</hi> ſad and deplorable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was given at the door, and at the ſame time the Houſe was Petitioned by his Siſter for a hearing of him by them, which was granted, and two Votes paſſed in order to it; firſt, that his Keeper ſhould with all ſpeed bring him, with the cauſe of his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the Parliament: and ſecondly, that a Frigot ſhould be ſent to fetch him from the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> where he was then pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner; About ſix weeks after he was brought to the Bar of the Houſe, by his Keeper, who produced no authority for his detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119184:3"/>but a bare command (without any cauſe expreſſed) from the late Uſurper; whereupon the Parliament voted his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment illegal and unjuſt; &amp; that firſt, becauſe no Chief Magiſtrate had ever power to commit any perſon by his own warrant: ſecondly, becauſe there was no cauſe axpreſſed in the Warrant: and thirdly, becauſe no man can according to Law be baniſhed, but by Act of Parliament; and ſo releaſed him from his impriſonment, without paying any fees or charges.</p>
            <p>The fifth of <hi>February</hi> a perſon who ſate in the Houſe, being found to be no Member, was for his offence therein committed to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> and not to the <hi>Tower,</hi> which is the Parliaments priſon, chiefly in regard of the preſent Lieutenants great exactions and oppreſſions, and partly, that upon inquiry, the offender was found to be under ſome degree of diſtraction.</p>
            <p>Upon the day appointed, the Bill for recogniſing the Protector, was read the ſecond time, and the debate begun: The <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> was pleaded by the Court party, as the foundation of his Title, but by thoſe that was for the Commonwealth it was denied to be a Law; and that not only from the inconſiſtency, lameneſs, and inſufficiency of it, but alſo from the corrupt manner of its procurement, that Aſſembly that made it being no Parliament, but a Faction, in that the members were never ſuffered to meet, but ſo many of them kept out even by him that called them, as he judged would hinder the execution of his will; beſides that at the creation of that monſter, there was but of 460. choſen, but 104. in the Houſe, whereof 51. was againſt it, and carried meerly by the ſtrength of Scotch and Iriſh members, who had no right to ſit, but were Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in the making Laws for <hi>England;</hi> It was further ſhewen, that if <hi>Caeſar Burgia,</hi> Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, and <hi>Matchivel,</hi> had all laid their heads together, they could not have framed a thing more deſtructive to the Liberties of the people, and for abſolute tyranny, giving away all that our anceſtors have fought for ever ſince the Conqueſt, Than the <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Advice,</hi> As the Negative Vote, The power of diſſolving Parliaments, The purſe of the people, and in that all the ſecurity they had for their Rights and Liberties; For, give the Single Perſon your purſe, and you give him the Militia; and if he have that, all bounding, of him by Lawes, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies no more than binding of a Lyon with paper Chaines.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119184:4"/>But the Courtiers being reſolved of nothing leſs than a Turkiſh power, would ſuffer no ſtrength of reaſon to prevail with them to the making of the <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> unauthentick but would by force allow it for a good Law; which provoked the demanding the purſuance of that Law to be proved, and that the pretenders deſignation was according as it is there directed; but though this was preſſed by divers perſons of great abilities, never any anſwer was given unto it; thoſe of that party knowing, that by the ſtrength of their Members, they could over-rule the ſtrength of Reaſon: It was from ſuch ſilence in the point of deſignation argued, that if Providence had prevented the Uſurper of keeping to the Rules of the <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Advice,</hi> and that it was thereby fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len to the ground, all Government was reverted to its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal (the People) and ought by them aſſembled in Parliament to be derived where ever it ſhould be ſeeked, which would readily have been done to the Gentleman in poſſeſſion, if he and his party would upon thoſe terms have accepted of it.</p>
            <p>This debate (no man ſpeaking twice to the matter) held eight dayes, in which time ſuperlative excellency and good affections to the publick appeared in ſeveral Gentlemen, yet the beſt end they could bring this debate unto, was to conclude with the two follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Votes, as previous to the commitment of the Bill.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="resolutions">
                        <opener>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Monday</hi> 14. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1658.</date>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That it be part of this Bill to recognize and declare his Highneſs <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Protector, to be Lord Protector and Chief Magiſtrate of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions and Territories thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That before this Bill be committed, this Houſe do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſuch additional Clauſes to be part of this Bill, as may bound the power of the Chief Magiſtrate, and fully ſecure the Rights and Privileges of the Parliament, and the Liberties and Rights of the people, and that neither this nor any other previous Vote that is, or ſhall be paſſed in order to this Bill, is, or ſhall be of force or bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto the people, until the whole Bill be paſſed.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119184:4"/>
This laſt previous Vote paſſed the Houſe without one Negative more then the Secretary; but when the Courtiers knew the ſenſe of <hi>White-Hall</hi> upon it, from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they owned themſelves ſuch ſlaviſh executioners of a pretenders will and luſt, that they never appeared in the leaſt for the making good one word of it.</p>
            <p>During this debate, ſeveral complaints was made (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the Court deſignes) as that the Aſſizes (without preſident, upon no greater occaſion) was put off, to the common wrong of the whole Nation; deſiring therefore, that to the end that the people might receive no prejudice by the ſitting of Parliament, nor have cauſe to be out of love with Parliaments, that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor might be moved to command the carrying on of the Aſſizes; but the Courtiers being reſolved not to loſe ſo conſiderable a part of their ſtrength as the Lawyers, they would have the whole Nation to ſuffer in the want of Juſtice, rather than they would want one of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>That <hi>White-Hall</hi> had writ eighty Letters for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king members of Parliament, moſt of which had had their effect. That <hi>Mr. Howard</hi> a Papiſt, and brother to the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> boaſted, that at the inſtance of the Protector and Secretary, he had ſent twenty four mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to Parliament. That ſeveral Tables were kept at <hi>White-Hall</hi> at the vaſt charge of the publick, on purpoſe to corrupt and deboiſt members by great entertainments; all which was acknowledged to be againſt the orders of the Houſe, and particularly for any members (not menial ſervants) to go to <hi>White-Hall</hi> during the ſitting of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>After this the Secretary gave an occaſion of forraign affairs, declaring a million of money needful for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraying the Naval expences for this Sommer, which brought on the debate concerning the Navy, in behalf of the publick; that as the Navy is part of the Militia, and the Militia the right of the people aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that without the Militia the Parliament could
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119184:5"/>not make good their promiſes to the people, in bounding the power of the chief Magiſtrate, and ſecuring their Rights and Liberities; That the Houſe would appoint certain Commiſſioners for management of the Naval forces; The debate for ſetting out a very Conſiderable fleet to Sea for Defence of the Commonwealth, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce hold not long; the thing being readily and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly agreed on: But who ſhould Manage the Fleet was a Debate of ſeveral days; and at laſt Carryed with a ſtrong hand by the Court party againſt all Reaſon and Policy that the Protector ſhould have the Diſpoſal of it; only the Commonwealths men got into the Vote that the making Peace and War ſhould be reſerved unto the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Portman</hi> a priſoner in the Tower, was upon his Petition brought before the Houſe, with the Cauſe of his impriſonment, The Warrant to the Lieutenant of the Tower for apprehending him was produced, and being onely from the Uſurper in theſe Words following;</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="warrant">
                        <p>Sir,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Dated Feb.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 57.</note> I deſire you to ceaze Major General <hi>Harriſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Carew, Portman,</hi> and ſuch as are eminent Fifth-Monarchy men, eſpecially <hi>Feake</hi> and <hi>Rogers;</hi> do it ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and you ſhall have a Warrant after you have done. The Parliament Voted his Impriſonment illegal and unjuſt, and freed him out of Priſon without paying either Fees or Charges. Several other Complaints of a higher Nature; as for Baniſhment and Selling of Gentlemen to the <hi>Barbadoes</hi> for Slaves, was before the Parliament, wherein they were prevented by their Diſſolution of doing any thing; but Mr. <hi>Maynard</hi> (then Called a Serjeant from the Uſurpers making) was Ordered to bring in a Bill for prevention of the like Tyranny in the future. The Accounts of the Commonwealth was Called for, and a Committee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Examine them and report the ſtate of them to the Houſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119184:5"/>
The Houſe was called upon to make good their Vote of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the power of the Chief Magiſtrate, and ſecuring the Rights, Priviledges and Liberties of the Parliament and people, and that as they had filled the hearts of all men with joy, in expectation of having their Rights aſcertained, that they would not render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Juglers, in promiſing what they never intended to perform. But to take the ſeveral parts of the previous Vote into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and as bounding the Chief Magiſtrate is firſt in order, ſo to begin with it. Yet ſuch was the diſ-ingenuity of the Court-party, being made up of Houſhold-ſervants, Officers of profit, ſuiters for Offices, Lawyers (the corrupt part of whoſe Trade, cannot be maintained but by a Corrupt Government) <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Members, choſen by the Pretender's Intereſt; that no Arguments of honour or honeſty could engage them to be Faithful to their Countrey: ſuch as were moſt open, confeſſing plainly that they were ſo far from bounding the Chief Magiſtrate, that they deſired to give him as much, nay more power then any King or Prince of <hi>England</hi> ever had, ſeeming to caſt Dirt upon the famous long Parliament (whoſe ſucceſſes and great Atchievments will by poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be had in Admiration) for aſſerting the Rights of the people againſt the Kings own perſon, not ſticking to charge them with murther for that War: and that without reproof, but rather conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from them. But others more prudent waved bounding of the Chief Magiſtrate, under pretence of firſt ſettling the Conſtitution of the Government; and ſo falling upon the Debate of that, after ſome days ſpent in it, at the laſt voted, that it ſhould be part of the Bill for Recognition to declare the Parliament to conſiſt of two Houſes. After this the Houſe was again put in mind of their duties to the people, and urged to fall upon bounding the power of the Chief Magiſtrate: which as it was firſt in Order, ought to have been firſt in Debate. But the Courtiers commanding all by the ſtrength of their Members, waved the Cheif Magiſtrate, and fell upon conſtituting the other Houſe, in which ſome dayes were ſpent in diſputes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the new &amp; old Royaliſts, the Commonwealths-men remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſilent, to ſee what the ſtrength of the others Brains would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. The firſt was for the new Creation of Lords, with the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the old, upon ſuch limitations as they might not over-top the new: The other for the old with a mixture of the new, and for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119184:6"/>the full priviledges of the ancient Houſes of Peers: but after it appeared, that they could make nothing of the Debate, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to truſt one another. The Commonwealth-men fell in, and ſhewed that where the Cauſe is taken away, the Effect muſt ceaſe. That as the Houſe of Lords had anciently a natural Right to a ſuperiour Jurisdiction, in that their propriety was five parts of ſix, of the whole Nation: ſo is it now more natural for the Commons, to have that Superiority; their proportion of propriety being ninty nine parts, or more, of a hundred. And therefore Moved, that if they would have another Houſe, it might be ſo bounded, as might ſuit with the people's Intereſt: whereupon they proceeded to the Debate of the Bounds and Powers of the Members ſitting in the other Houſe of Parliament, and begun with the other Houſe of Parliament, in which ſome days was ſpent, they being but for life, for that it is againſt the Common Law for any one to be a Judge for him and his Heirs for ever. Then for their being firſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and approved of by the Parliament. Then upon their having Negatives only in ſome matters. Yet ended none, but at laſt diſ-ingenuouſly laid all aſide; and, in ſtead of bounding and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of them: a bare Queſtion was brought on foot, Whether the members ſitting in the other Houſe, as then conſtituted, ſhould be tranſacted with or no, thereby to let them at once into the full priviledges of the ancient Lords, and to make it paſſe the ſmoothlier. A plauſible Cauſe, to ſave the Rights of the ancient Peers, was added by the Courtiers, which was done only to gain the Cavaliers in that Vote, and not with any intent to let in the Lords: they confeſſing occaſionally, that the Rights of the ancient Peers could be nothing, ſo long as the act for taking of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way was in being, and un-repealed. Againſt acting with the Members ſitting in the other Houſe as then Conſtituted, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged the inconſiſtency of it with the Rights and Liberties of the People, which they had ſworn to maintain. As firſt, in that they were moſt dependants upon the Single perſon by way of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries: and ſo likely to be his Mercenaries. Secondly, for that the Militia both by Sea and Land was in the hands of the perſons then ſitting in that Houſe. Thirdly, That all the chief Judges were Members: as the three Keepers of the Seal, two Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Maſter of the Rowls: and that it might well be thought,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119184:6"/>that the Lord chief Barron would be accounted as worthy to be one as the reſt. And then the people in all Caſes of Appeales, could do no more then Appeal from the Judges in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, to the ſame perſons ſitting in Parliament. And that the chief Judicature being in that Houſe, and having the Militia to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; That Houſe might wrong the Commons as they pleaſed, and they remain without Remedy. Fourthly, That all the Privy Council, the chief Judges, and General Officers, both by Sea and Land, being Members; The Lawyers and Officers of profit (of whom the Body of the Houſe of Commons would be made up) would be the Creatures and Mercenaries of one or other of them of the other Houſe: and ſo make the Houſe of Commons to be nothing but the Executioners of their Lords and Maſters Will's; But notwithſtanding theſe and many more excellent Arguments incomparably preſſed by perſons of great Vertue and Abilities, the ſervile and mercenary Court-party would not be prevailed with to bound and approve the Members ſitting in the other Houſe, before they put it to the Vote for tranſacting with them: which made the Commonwealths-men immediately, as the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was coming on, to except againſt the Conſtitution of the Houſe, as having ſixty perſons in it ſent from <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> which had no Right nor Title to ſit, which they did as being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to venture the Queſtion for the tranſacting with the other Houſe, without firſt bounding and approving therewith. With this new-ſtarted exception, which held afterwards fourteen dayes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the Houſe riſſe, and the next day Mr. <hi>Chute,</hi> their Worthy and Impartial Speaker, finding himſelf indiſpoſed, deſired to be diſmiſſed the ſervice; but the Houſe valuing him at a high Rate, would not accept of his Reſignation, but diſpenſed with his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance untill he ſhould recover his health, by withdrawing into the Countrey, or otherwiſe as he ſhould think fit; and, to ſupply his place in the mean time, Mr. <hi>Long,</hi> Recorder of <hi>London</hi> was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, but it pleaſed God, the great Diſpoſer of all things to end both their dayes before the end of the Parliament; taking away the latter firſt, in whoſe room as ſupplying Mr. <hi>Chutes</hi>'s place, was choſen Mr. <hi>Bamfield,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chute</hi> being yet living, though lived not to come any more unto the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The Debate concerning the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Members, came on,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119184:7"/>which run ſeveral wayes: The Courtiers after they found the want of Law, flew to Prudence, arguing that for obliging the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nations, their Members ought to be admitted: to which was anſwered, that nothing could be more provoking to thoſe two Nations, then fraudulently to give them the Name of having Members in Parliament: when in truth by the late Elections they had few or none, moſt of them being choſen at <hi>White hall,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome had hardly been ever nearer <hi>Scotland</hi> then <hi>Grayes-Inne.</hi> But beſides this anſwer to the Courtiers Arguments of Prudence; The Commonwealths men, argued againſt their ſitting, as having no legal Right or Title, to ſit, and that without keeping to legal Rules, Foundations could not be maintained; for otherwiſe they that ſent ſixty now, might ſend three hundred next time: and ſo make Parliaments of what number and temper they pleaſed: and therefore would that the Members of both Nations might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and be afterwards brought in upon legal and equal feet: But <hi>White hall</hi> being reſolved not to part with any of their ſtrength (though after they had done their Work, they intended to have caſt them off) would have nothing to do with Law or Right, and therefore whereas the Queſtion ſhould have been, Whether the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Members had any legal Right to ſit, the words <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right</hi> was thrown out. And the bare queſtion put, <hi>Whether the</hi> Scotch <hi>and</hi> Iriſh <hi>Members ſhould ſit?</hi> And, by the help of the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who were ſuffered contrary to the Law of nature to Vote in their own Caſe; It was carried that they ſhould ſit in Parliament. In which Vote, the Parliament may be ſaid to have betrayed their truſt, in taking in ſtrangers without Law to make Laws for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation: and in not puniſhing the Keepers of the Seal: who preſumptuouſly took upon them without and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Law to ſend ſixty Stangers as Members to Parliament.</p>
            <p>After this, the main Queſtion, for tranſacting with the other Houſe, before-bounded or approved, which had been interrupted by the Debate about the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Members came on again, It was endeavouring to get the Words <hi>Bounding</hi> and <hi>Approving</hi> the Members into the Queſtion; but they were thrown out by a Vote, and the bare queſtion put; <hi>Whether they ſhould be tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with or no, as then Conſtituted,</hi> only the Commonwealths-men got the words, <hi>during this preſent Parliament,</hi> into the queſtion:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119184:7"/>and then by the help of the Scotch and Iriſh Votes, by whoſe number all queſtions was carryed in favour of the Court, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to tranſact with the perſons then ſitting in the Other Houſe of Parliament, during this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Report of the Committee concerning the Accompts of the Commonwealth was brought in; By it appeared much bad husbandry, and ill Government in the laſt 5 years: Several Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being created to ſerve perſons and make Creatures, without having in them any eye to the publick, inſomuch that, whereas at the interruption of Government, the Commonwealth (reckoning the ready mony in Caſh, the Army's payed ſome months before hand, and the ſtores newly laid in) might be accompted rich, they are now neer two Millions and a half in debt.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Mary Huet</hi> petitioned the Grand Committee of the whole Houſe for grievances, againſt the High Court of Jufl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, for unjuſtly taking away the life of her Husband: but ſome Members declaring themſelvs concerned, and it being the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a Member not to be petitioned againſt, any where but to the Parliament, the Petition was returned her with that Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>A publick Faſt through the three Nations was voted, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for the ſame, from the Commons and the Protector on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, was ordered to be brought in: But the Court party, to the end to ingage the tranſacting with the other houſe, brought in the Declaration in the form of a Bill to be made an Act, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the expence of ſome daies in debating in what manner and form to ſend it to the Other Houſe, for that the firſt tranſaction would be the Rule for the future: It was in order thereunto vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, That the Commons would not ſhew the Other Houſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect then they ſhould ſhew to them. Secondly, That they would ſend Members of their own to the Other Houſe, and that they would receive no Meſſages from them but by Members of their own number. This was all the Votes of publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment that was carried in the whole time of the Parliament, which was either honourable or advantagious for the Commons, and yet the Courtiers, after they had conſulted with <hi>White-Hall,</hi> were reſolved to have unvoted and made it null and void: It was under debate what Ceremony the Meſſenger ſhould uſe at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119184:8"/>into their Houſe, and what Title to give them; <hi>Mr. Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, My Lord Commiſſioner,</hi> and <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> was all ſeverally ſpoken of, but none agreed on; and the Courtiers haſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as they could not ſtay, the Meſſenger that carryed the Act for the Faſt down to the Other Houſe, was adviſed to give them no Title at all, which directions he followed, and ſo left the Bill with them, which was never retured. During this debate ſome exceptions being taken at Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>'s carriage as unequal; he was accuſed of having had Conference at <hi>White-Hall</hi> with the Pretender, as that which was contrary to the orders of the Houſe; This Charge put the Houſe into a great heat, ſome taking part with him, and ſome againſt him, and as the Courtiers were not onely moſt in number but beſt at brawling, ſo they made the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt noiſe, untill they obſerved matter of truth in the thing; and then as the party charging was ſatisfied with giving the reproof, ſo the Courtiers were willing to have it dye. Some deficiency was obſerved by the Court in the Acts for forcing the payment of the Exciſe, and therefore a Bill was brought in by one of that party, under a ſpecious pretence of ſetling it but for a certain number of years, as the Parliament ſhould agree on, whereas it was ſetled for ever. This Bill after long debate, was by means of Common-wealths-men laied aſide, and a Declaration brought in by them to injoyn the payment of the Exciſe during the ſitting of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, owning clearly their deſigne to be, That if the Laws were not good, the aſcertaining the Exciſe no longer then during the Parliament, would put a neceſſity upon the Chief Magiſtrate to let the Parliament ſit untill they had done ſome good for the poor people of <hi>England;</hi> and if they were good, the Declaration did not prejudice them: But as the Commonwealths-men laid aſide the Courtiers Bill, ſo they laied aſide the Commonwealths-mens Declaration.</p>
            <p>The Parliament fell upon the Accompts of the Common-wealth again, conſidered how to retrench the Charges, bring the disburſements not to exceed the income, raiſe preſent money for the Army out of the Arrears owing the ſtate, and other waies if poſſile, without laying any new Tax (which the Court party was much for) upon the People: But in this they were interrupted by the Courtiers, who brought on foot, 1. To vote all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119184:8"/>Officers of the Army to go to their ſeverall Charges. 2. That they ſhould hold no meeting during the ſitting of Parliament, but by conſent of the Protector and both Houſes. 3. That none ſhould be in Office but ſuch as would ſubſcribe not to interrupt either Houſe of Parliament in their debates <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Votes were ſent down to the Other Houſe where they remain'd unretur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The next day the Accompts were ſallen upon again, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted the ſecond time by the Courtiers, who brought on foot the queſtion; Where the right of the <hi>Militia</hi> did reſide? with a deſigne, firſt, to vote it in the Protector and both Houſes of Parl. And ſecondly, to vote the Protector General, knowing that in ſuch Caſe the Parliaments Intereſt in it, even during their ſitting, would have ſignified nothing, and after they were diſſolved it would fall naturally to the Protector ſoly, becauſe no other power pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it would be in being; but in this buſineſſe they could not come to a Queſtion that night though ſtriven hard for by the Court party who was ſo eager upon it, that when it was deſired that they would but conſult the declarations of the Parliament, and the Kings Conceſſions thereupon concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> that ſo they might not raſhly give away from the people what the King had granted to be their right; they would not indure the reading of them, leſt they could not for ſhame make the people Slaves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their eyes were open, which they were reſolved blindfolded to do. The next day being the 22 of <hi>April,</hi> the black Rod came to the door to have entrance. The Serjeant, who ſhould have done no more then acquainted the Houſe that ſuch a Meſſenger was at the door, acquainted them with his Meſſage, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That by order of the Protector, the Speaker of the other Houſe ſent to the Houſe of Commons to come with their Speaker to them in the Other Houſe: which the Houſe received generally with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and ſcorne, ſome ſaying They were the Upper Houſe, and ſo without receiving the Meſſenger, the Houſe adjourned till Munday the 25th of <hi>April:</hi> But the next day the pretended Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector diſſolved the pretended Parliament by a Proclamation.</p>
            <p>This is a brief Relation of the moſt material debates of the late Parliament, many private and ſome publick buſineſſes of leſſer concernment being omitted.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole it may be obſerved, that as the Court had by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119184:9"/>the advantages which alwaies follow the Authority of the Chief Magiſtrate, ſo packed the Parliament, that the over-ruling Vote was at their Command; So the perſons of that party were of ſuch ſervile and mercenary principles, that they knew no publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, nor any other then the private Intereſt of the ſingle Perſon, and their own.</p>
            <p>That all that the Commonwealths-men were able to do was to defer and keep off Slavery for a ſmall time (in hope that God would ſend deliverance) without power of doing any more good, then by ſometimes getting a qualifying word into a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For,</p>
            <p>If the Parliament had ſate longer, the Commonwealths-men could not have preſerved the Liberties of the Nation many weeks more, from the ruines the Couriers had deſigned. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Diſſolution of it may well be looked upon as a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance equal with that from the Gunpowder-Plot.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, That as the old Monarchy, The Houſe Lords, the Biſhops, and the Presbyterians, were all, in their ſeveral Intereſts, ſeverally deſtroyed, by their ſeveral endeavours to maintain the corrupt parts of each ſeverall Intereſt; So the down-fall of the new Monarchy hath proceeded from the ſame Cauſe. For would a moderate power have ſatisfyed the Pretender and his party, it had been readily yielded, the Commonwealths-men being ſo low in their hopes of what God hath ſince wonderfully brought about, that they would have been glad of any indifferent terms for the good People of this Nation, for whom many and deep Pits were digged, but God hath delivered them out of all.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
